Finding Aid for Douglas D. Crary Papers, 1943-2003
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Douglas D. Crary papers
1943-2003
1965-1973
Crary, Douglas D., 1910-
91455 Aa 2
Papers of Douglas D. Crary (1910-2005), professor of geography at the University of Michigan, Ann Arbor City Council member, and active participant in numerous civic and community affairs, particularly those related to development and planning. The series in the collection are: Municipal Affairs; University of Michigan; Political Affairs; Huron River Watershed Council; Community Activity; Ann Arbor Planning Commission; Clippings; Miscellaneous local activities; and World War II activities.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
21 linear feet
The bulk of the collection was donated by Douglas D. Crary (Donor no. 4935 ) in 1990; subsequent donations were made by his estate in 2006-2011.
The collection is open to research.
Douglas D. Crary first came to Ann Arbor in 1929 as an undergraduate at the University of Michigan. Following completion of undergraduate and graduate studies, Crary accepted a professorship in the University's Department of Geography in 1941. In the mid-1950s, Crary, his wife and their four children spent a year traveling throughout Africa as part of his sabbatical work. He retired from the University in 1973.
In addition to his professorial duties, Crary took an interest in the administrative affairs of the University, serving on the President's Commission for Off-Campus Housing in 1965. In 1965, Crary was elected to the Ann Arbor City Council as Republican councilman from the Second Ward, and was re-elected to this seat in 1967.
During his tenure on the Council, Crary served on a number of committees, notably the Housing Committee and the Bus Committee. After retiring from the Council in 1969, Crary continued to be active in civic and community affairs. He served on the board of the Huron River Watershed Council as well as the City Planning Commission in the early 1970s, and on the boards of the Ann Arbor Art Association and the Ecumenical Campus Center during the 1980s. Other organizations with which Crary was involved included the Washtenaw County Land Conservancy Board, the Washtenaw County Planning Commission, the Ann Arbor Historical Foundation, and the Ann Arbor Sesquicentennial Commission.
The personal papers of Douglas Crary reflect his public activities rather than his private life. The papers have been divided into nine series: Municipal Affairs, 1962-1976; University of Michigan, 1965; Political Affairs, 1964-1970; Huron River Watershed Council, 1965-1973; Community Activity, 1981-1988; Ann Arbor Planning Commission, 1965-1977; Clippings, circa 1965-1980, Miscellaneous local activities; and World War II activities.
Subjects:
Ann Arbor (Mich.); Ann Arbor Art Association.; Ann Arbor (Mich.). Common Council.; Ann Arbor (Mich.). Planning Commission.; Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Politics and government.; Campus Ecumenical Center (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Crary, Douglas D., 1910-; Huron River Watershed Council.; Municipal government--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan--Administration.Administration.; United States. Civil Affairs Training School (University of Michigan); University of Michigan--Student housing.Student housing.
Subjects: Visual Materials
Ann Arbor (Mich.); Ann Arbor Antiques Market.; Antique stores--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Vaccinations--Michigan.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Municipal Affairs, 1962-1976
  The first series, Municipal Affairs, includes both records from Crary's tenure on the City Council and Planning Commission, and is arranged alphabetically by topic. This series is an excellent resource for those interested in the operations of municipal government, as well as those interested in the considerations involved in urban planning for a rapidly expanding city. Topics range from the mundane, such as the city's dog and cat ordinance, to more significant issues such as the creation and implementation of the Ann Arbor Transportation Authority, (found in the transportation files). In addition, the series reflects the myriad of issues with which a small city government must contend. It contains information on finances, feasibility, and public opinion. These files document municipal affairs from a number of angles.
  Those interested in the social history of Ann Arbor can find useful information in this series. Information about the increasing need for low income housing during the mid-1960s, as well as a discussion of racial segregation during this period, is located both under housing files and in the human relations files. The tensions between the community and the University of Michigan student body, on the rise during the late 1960s, (heyday of student activism) are documented in files on student activism and the City-University Relations Committee.
  The public's varied attitude towards city government is well documented in the correspondence file of the municipal series, which contains, among other items, suggestions for street names from Gretchen, aged ten, praise for the police department, threats to sue the city for various mishaps, and allegations that the inefficiency of Ann Arbor's city government reflects the downfall of the democratic system in modern times. Apart from the municipal records, those of the Huron River Watershed Council document the increasing concern for natural resource protection and management that began to take hold in the late 1960s and early 1970s. The council, along with several others in Michigan, worked to develop plans that would service the industrial and recreational needs of the growing region without destroying its water and land resources.
  - Administrator (Box 1)
  - Administrator's Activity Reports and Programs, 1965-1971; 1 volumes (Box 1)
  - Administrator's Reports, 1972; 1 volumes (Box 1)
  - Administrator's Development Committee, 1966-1968 (Box 1)
  - Airport Advisory Committee, 1963-1969 (Box 1)
  - Air Pollution Control Ordinance, 1967 (Box 1)
  - All America Cities Competition, 1966 (Box 1)
  - Ann Arbor Area Goals, 1966-1969 (Box 1)
  - Ann Arbor Community Development Inc., 1966 (Box 1)
  - Ann Arbor Hills, 1965-1967 (Box 1)
  - Assessor, 1968-1969 (Box 1)
  - Atomic Energy Commission, 1966-1967 (Box 1)
  - Attorney, 1961-1969 (Box 1)
  - Bader Parent-Teacher Organization (PTO), 1966 (Box 1)
  - Bird Hills Park/Kuebler Property Rezoning, 1968-1972 (Box 1)
  - Board of Appeals
    - Building, 1966-1968 (Box 1)
    - Housing, 1968 (Box 1)
    - Signs, 1968-1972 (Box 1)
    - Zoning, 1963-1973 (Box 1)
  - Board of Insurance Administration, 1965-1969 (Box 2)
  - Bonding Procedure, undated (Box 2)
  - Building and Safety Engineering, 1967-1968 (Box 2)
  - Building Authority, 1966-1969 (Box 2)
  - Building Code Enforcement Study, 1969 (Box 2)
  - Budget, 1965-1968 (Box 2)
  - Community Access Television (CATV), 1965-1972 (Box 2)
  - Capital Improvements, 1966-1968 (Box 2)
  - Charter Amendment Committee, 1965-1967; 1 volumes (Box 2)
  - City-School Board Relations Committee, 1965-1973 (Box 2)
  - City-University Relations Committee, 1962-1975 (Box 2)
  - Civil Defense, 1965-1968 (Box 2)
  - Civil Rights, 1965-1966 (Box 2)
  - Clean-Up, Paint-Up, Fix Up Committee, 1965-1966 (Box 2)
  - Clean-Up, City Beautiful, 1965-1966; 1 volumes (Box 2)
  - Clerk, 1966-1969 (Box 3)
  - Community College, 1963-1965; 1987 (Box 3)
  - Controller, 1966-1967 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1965-1969 (Box 3)
  - Cultural Centers, 1972 (Box 3)
  - Damage Deposits, 1969 (Box 3)
  - Data Processing, 1966-1969 (Box 3)
  - Day Care-Nursery Issue (Gay Jay School zoning), 1967 (Box 3)
  - Dean Fund, 1965-1969 (Box 3)
  - Design Review Board, 1971-1972 (Box 3)
  - Dog and Cat Control Ordinance, 1967-1968; 1973 (Box 3)
  - Dutch Elm Disease, 1968-1973 (Box 3)
  - Economic Development and Manpower Commission, 1966 (Box 3)
  - Efficiency Committee, 1965-1969 (Box 3)
  - Environmental Interpretive Center, 1967-1969 (Box 3)
  - Federal Grants, 1966-1972 (Box 3)
  - Finance, Blue Ribbon Committee on, 1967-1971; 1 volumes (Box 3)
  - Finance and Taxation, 1967-1968; 1 volumes (Box 3)
  - Gun Control, 1968-1970 (Box 3)
  - Health Department, 1965-1968 (Box 3)
  - Housing
    - General, 1 folders (Box 3)
    - General, 1967-1972; 5 folders (Box 4)
    - Housing Commission, 1967-1969 (Box 4)
    - Housing Committee, 1965-1966; 3 folders (Box 4)
    - Fair Housing, 1963-1965; 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Housing Emergency Loan Program (H.E.L.P.), 1968-1969 (Box 4)
    - Public Housing, 1967-1968 (Box 4)
  - Human Relations Commission
    - General, 1965-1968; 4 folders (Box 5)
    - Community Profile, 1967 (Box 5)
    - Population Distribution of Racial Minorities in Ann Arbor, Michigan, 1950-1960 (Box 5)
  - Huron Parkway-Bridge, 1964-1968 (Box 5)
  - Huron River Dams Bond Issue Citizens' Committee, 1970-1973 (Box 5)
  - International Commission (Box 5)
  - Labor, 1965-1969 (Box 5)
  - Liquor Committee, 1965-1969 (Box 5)
  - Market Commission, 1965-1969 (Box 5)
  - Mayor, 1965-1973 (Box 5)
  - Model Cities Program, 1966-1969; 1 volumes (Box 6)
  - Motorcycle Ordinance, 1966-1967 (Box 6)
  - Municipal Court, 1966-1968 (Box 6)
  - Natural Resources Advisory Committee, 1965 (Box 6)
  - Noise Ordinance, 1968 (Box 6)
  - North Central Area, 1967 (Box 6)
  - Office of Equal Opportunity, 1967-1968 (Box 6)
  - Old West Side, 1966-1976 (Box 6)
  - Packard Road, 1966-1969 (Box 6)
  - Parking
    - Parking and Traffic Engineering, 1965-1973 (Box 6)
    - Parking Structures, 1965-1969 (Box 6)
    - Student Parking, 1965-1969 (Box 6)
  - Parks
    - Bond Proposals (Parkways), 1965-1967 (Box 6)
    - Bond Proposals, 1971-1972 (Box 6)
    - Department, 1965-1976 (Box 6)
  - Peddlers and Solicitors Ordinance, 1966-1975 (Box 6)
  - Pensions and Retirements Board, 1965-1969 (Box 6)
  - Personnel Department, 1966-1969 (Box 6)
  - Personnel and Salary, 1965-1968 (Box 6)
  - Planning Department, 1969-1972 (Box 6)
  - Police-Community Relations, 1965-1968 (Box 6)
  - Police Department, 1965-1968 (Box 6)
  - Project '74, 1965-1967 (Box 6)
  - Project 74, 1964 (Box 7)
  - Public Improvement Fund, 1967 (Box 7)
  - Public Works, 1965-1973 (Box 7)
  - Recreation Advisory Board, 1965-1969 (Box 7)
  - Scenic Easements, 1965-1967 (Box 7)
  - Senior Citizens Guild, 1966-1967 (Box 7)
  - Side Walks and School Crossings, 1968-1970 (Box 7)
  - Sign Ordinance, 1966-1973; 5 folders (Box 7)
  - Site Plans, 1965-1973 (Box 7)
  - Special Assessment Committee, 1965-1968 (Box 7)
  - Student Activism, 1966-1970 (Box 8)
  - Teen Center, 1967 (Box 8)
  - Transportation
    - General, 1967-1971; 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Ann Arbor Transportation Authority, 1965-1971; 3 folders (Box 8)
    - Bicycle Path Study, 1972 (Box 8)
    - Bus Committee, 1966-1967 (Box 8)
    - Taxicab Board, 1965-1971 (Box 8)
    - Thoroughfare Studies, 1964-1971 (Box 8)
    - Thoroughfare Studies, 1965-1970 (Box 9)
  - Treasurer, 1965-1968 (Box 9)
  - University of Michigan Sesquicentennial Commission, 1965-1967 (Box 9)
  - Underground Wires, 1968-1971 (Box 9)
  - Utilities Department, 1965-1973 (Box 9)
  - Washtenaw County
    - General, 1967-1968 (Box 9)
    - Bond Proposals, 1966-1970 (Box 9)
    - Citizen's Committee for Economic Opportunity, 1966-1968 (Box 9)
  - Workable Program, 1964-1969 (Box 9)
  - Youth Commission, 1965-1969 (Box 9)
- University of Michigan, 1965
  The second series, University of Michigan, contains reports from the President's Commission on Off-Campus Housing.
  - President's Commission on Housing, 1965 (Box 9)
- Political Affairs, 1964-1970
  The third series, Political Affairs, contains campaign materials and correspondence from the 1965, 1967, and 1969 elections, Republican organizational newsletters, and a strong collection of newspaper clippings about the city candidates and issues during the period Crary was active in city government.
  - Ann Arbor City Council Campaigns
    - 1965, 2 folders (Box 10)
    - 1967, 2 folders (Box 10)
    - 1969, 3 folders (Box 10)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1965-1968 (Box 17)
  - Republican Affairs, 1964-1970; 3 folders (Box 10)
- Huron River Watershed Council, 1965-1973
  The fourth series, regarding the Huron River Watershed Council, includes minutes of meetings, bylaws, resolutions, reports, and correspondence with other similar councils in Michigan. General records have been arranged chronologically, along with a separate subseries for records relating to specific Watershed Council Development projects.
  - Administrative, 1968-1973 (Box 10)
  - Annual Reports, 1972-1973 (Box 10)
  - General, 1965-1973; 3 folders (Box 10)
  - Chronological
    - 1965-1969, 3 folders (Box 11)
    - 1969-1972, 4 folders (Box 11)
    - 1972-1973, 2 folders (Box 11)
  - Special Projects
    - General, 1970-1972 (Box 11)
    - Canoe Trail, 1967-1971 (Box 11)
    - Flooding, 1967-1968 (Box 11)
    - Management District, 1968 (Box 11)
    - Mill Creek, 1965-1970; 3 folders (Box 11)
    - Pointe Mouillee (Box 11)
- Community Activity, 1981-1988
  The fifth series, Community Activities, contains board minutes and newsletters from the Ecumenical Campus Center and the Ann Arbor Art Association, organizations for which Crary served as a board member during the late 1970s and 1980s.
  - Ann Arbor Art Association, 1981-1986 (Box 12)
  - Ecumenical Campus Community Center, 1977-1988 (Box 12)
- Ann Arbor Planning Commission, 1965-1977
  The Ann Arbor Planning Commission series comprises the three-ring binders of reference material Crary kept regarding his work on the Commission. The materials have been removed from their original binders for easier access and storage, but their contents and titles remain intact. The series is divided between chronological files and topical files, both spanning the same time period.
  - Chronological
    - 1965-1969, 5 folders (Box 12)
    - 1970-1975, 7 folders (Box 13)
    - Unlabeled, 1972-1973; 2 folders (Box 14)
  - Topical
    - Agricultural Lands Committee (Box 14)
    - Alumni Living and Oxford Housing (Box 14)
    - Area Planning -- Township Relations -- Utilities (Box 14)
    - Briarwood (Box 14)
    - Capital Improvement Budget / Program, 1972-1977 (Box 14)
    - CBD Hi-Rise and Parking (Box 14)
    - Central City -- Planned Unit Development (Box 15)
      (P.U.D.)
    - Commission Procedures -- Citizen Participation (Box 15)
    - Community Renewal Program (Box 15)
    - Garden Homes (Box 15)
    - General Development Plan (Box 15)
    - Guide to Change (Box 15)
    - Interim Committee for Development Policies for Areas Surrounding Washtenaw Community College (Box 15)
    - Landscape Ordinance (Box 15)
    - Miscellaneous Zoning Matters, 2 folders (Box 15)
    - Parks and Recreation (Box 16)
    - Pittsfield Valley Area Survey (Box 16)
    - Plans and Zones (Box 16)
    - Planning Priorities (Box 16)
    - R2B District Survey (Box 16)
    - R4 Density Survey (Box 16)
    - Shopping Centers (Box 16)
    - Sign Ordinance Review Committee (Box 16)
    - Southwest Ann Arbor / Airport (Box 17)
    - State Land Use Act (Box 17)
    - Subdivision and Land Use Control Ordinance (Box 17)
    - Washtenaw Land Conservancy (Box 17)
    - West Stadium Boulevard (Box 17)
    - Zoning Ordinance (Box 17)
- Clippings, circa 1965-1980
  Like the Ann Arbor Planning Commission series, the Clippings include both topical and chronological files, each spanning the same time period. The topical files cover a broad variety of topics, including day care, environmental concerns, historical preservation, and taxes. The chronological files primarily contain campaign advertisements for local elections, editorials and news stories related to local politics and politicians. In this way, the chronological files compliment the earlier series, Political Affairs, 1964-1970.
  - Topical
    - Airport and Issue (Box 18)
    - Annexation Growth
      - Through, 1970 (Box 18)
      - 1971-1972 (Box 18)
      - 1973-circa 1980 (Box 18)
    - Beautification (Box 18)
    - Bicycles (Box 18)
    - Bottle Ban, 3 folders (Box 18)
    - Briarwood (Box 18)
    - Budget
      - Through, 1972 (Box 18)
      - 1973-1974 (Box 18)
      - 1975-circa 1980 (Box 18)
    - Cable Television (CATV) (Box 18)
    - Central Business District (CBD)
      - Through, 1973 (Box 18)
      - 1974 (Box 18)
      - 1975 (Box 18)
      - 1976-circa 1980 (Box 18)
    - Code Enforcement (Box 18)
    - Day Care Centers (Box 18)
    - Detergents -- Phosphates / Aerosols (Box 18)
    - Dog Control Ordnance (Box 18)
    - Drugs (Box 18)
    - Employment (Box 18)
    - Ecology Center (Box 18)
    - Enact Teach-In (Box 18)
    - Environment
      - General and Political
        - Through, 1969 (Box 18)
        - 1970 (Box 18)
        - 1971-1972 (Box 18)
        - 1973-1974 (Box 18)
        - 1975-1976 (Box 18)
        - Undated (Box 18)
      - Great Lakes (Box 18)
        (includes Esch)
    - Environmental Law (Box 18)
    - Floods (Box 18)
    - Gardening (Box 18)
    - Hill and Onondaga (Box 18)
    - Hill Street Report (Box 18)
    - History of Ann Arbor (Box 18)
    - Historic Preservation
      - Through, 1973 (Box 18)
      - 1974-circa 1980 (Box 18)
      - Cobblestone Farm (Box 18)
      - Gandy Dancer Issue (Box 18)
    - Housing
      - Private
        - Through, 1972 (Box 19)
        - 1973 (Box 19)
      - Public
        - Through, 1969 (Box 19)
        - 1970-1973 (Box 19)
        - 1974-circa 1980 (Box 19)
    - Human Rights Services, 2 folders (Box 19)
    - Huron River (Box 19)
    - Judicial Reform Lobbying (Box 19)
    - Junk Yard Issue and Development (Box 19)
    - Leland, Etc.
      - Through, 1972 (Box 19)
      - 1973-1978 (Box 19)
    - Lifestyle (Box 19)
    - Litter Clean-Ups (Box 19)
    - Mill Creek Park (Box 19)
    - Miscellaneous
      - Anti-Rape Program (Box 19)
      - Consumer Ordinance (Box 19)
      - Crematorium (Box 19)
      - Education (Box 19)
      - Jewish Center Aid (Box 19)
      - Junior Achievement (Box 19)
      - Weed and Snow Removal (Box 19)
    - Model Cities
      - Through, 1971 (Box 19)
      - 1972- (Box 19)
    - Noise Pollution (Box 19)
    - Nuclear Power Plant Pollution (Box 19)
    - Office of Economic Opportunity (OEO) -- ADC (Box 19)
    - Organization (Box 19)
    - Parental Responsibility (Box 19)
    - Parking and Traffic (Box 19)
    - Parks
      - Through, 1971 (Box 19)
      - 1972-1974 (Box 19)
      - 1975-circa 1980 (Box 19)
    - Planning
      - Local
        - Through, 1970 (Box 19)
        - 1971-1972 (Box 19)
        - 1973 (Box 19)
        - 1974 (Box 19)
        - 1975-1976 (Box 19)
        - 1977-circa 1980 (Box 19)
      - General
        - Through, 1969 (Box 19)
        - 1970-circa 1980 (Box 19)
    - Police -- Community Relations (Box 19)
    - Population Control (Box 19)
    - Preferential Voting (Box 19)
    - Recycling Solid Waste
      - Through, 1972 (Box 19)
      - 1973-1976 (Box 19)
      - 1977-circa 1980 (Box 19)
    - Roads and Parkways
      - Through, 1973 (Box 19)
      - 1974-circa 1980 (Box 19)
    - St. John's
      - Through, 1972 (Box 19)
      - 1973-circa 1980 (Box 19)
    - Southeast Michigan Council of Governments (SEMCOG) (Box 19)
    - Sewer and Water
      - Through, 1972 (Box 20)
      - 1973-1974 (Box 20)
      - 1975-circa 1980 (Box 20)
    - Shopping Centers
      - Through, 1973 (Box 20)
      - 1974-circa 1980 (Box 20)
    - Super Sewer
      - Through, 1972 (Box 20)
      - 1973-1974 (Box 20)
      - 1975-circa 1980 (Box 20)
    - Taxation
      - Through, 1968 (Box 20)
      - 1969 (Box 20)
      - 1970-1971 (Box 20)
      - 1972-1974 (Box 20)
      - 1975-circa 1980 (Box 20)
    - Transportation
      - Local
        - Through, 1972 (Box 20)
        - 1973-1974 (Box 20)
        - 1975-circa 1980 (Box 20)
      - General (Box 20)
    - University of Michigan -- Community (Box 20)
    - Upper Peninsula (Box 20)
    - Washtenaw County, 2 folders (Box 20)
  - Chronological
    - 1969 (Box 20)
    - April 1970-August 1973, 41 folders (Box 20)
- Miscellaneous local activities
  Miscellaneous local activities includes files relating to Crary's activities with the Ann Arbor Historical Foundation, the Citizen's Millage Committee, and the Sign Ordinance Task Force.
  - Ann Arbor Bicentennial Commission, 1976 (Box 21)
  - Ann Arbor Historical Foundation, 1978-2003 (Box 21)
  - Citizen's Millage Committee, 1989-1993 (Box 21)
  - Kempf House Center for Local History (Box 21)
  - Sign Ordinance Task Force, 1998-1999 (Box 21)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 21)
  - Photographs (Box 21)
- World War II Activities
  The World War II activities series consists of course materials, publications, bulletins, and reports from the period when Crary taught in the East Asia Area Program of the Army Specialized Training Program at the University of Michigan.
  - Army Specialized Training Program -- East Asia Area Program, 1943-1945
    - Course syllabi, outlines, examinations, and other course material, 1 volumes; 13 folders (Box 21)
  - Civil Affairs Training School Far Eastern Program (Japan)
    - Final Report, University of Michigan, October 15, 1945 (Box 21)
    - Reports from other universities, 3 reports (Box 21)